Guide to the Benjamin Freeman Kendall Papers 1853-1916
Oregon Historical Society, Research Library
Benjamin Freeman Kendall papers.
1853-1916
1855-1862
Oregon Historical Society, Davies Family Research Library Research Library 1200 SW Park Avenue Portland, Oregon 97205 Phone: 503-306-5240 Fax: 503-219-2040 E-mail: libreference@ohs.org
Mss 1038
Kendall, B. F. (Benjamin Freeman), 1829-1863.
.45 cubic feet (1 document case)
Papers of an early Indian agent, political figure, and publisher of the Overland Press in Washington Territory. Includes correspondence, financial records, and papers relating to the Indian agency.
Biography of Benjamin Freeman Kendall:
Benjamin Freeman Kendall was a political figure and Indian agent in early Washington Territory. He owned and operated the newspaper Overland Press in Olympia, and it was there that he wrote of the incendiary activities of a Mr. Howe, a farmer of Ford's Prairie. Howe and Kendall began a feud which culminated in fight in the streets of Olympia in late 1862, Howe being wounded by Kendall's gunfire. This resulted in an incident in January of 1863 in which Howe's son Horace shot and killed Kendall at the latter's office in Olympia. Howe was arrested but acquitted, and it was rumored that Kendall's political enemies may have precipitated the assassination.
The collection consists primarily of correspondence, financial records, and legal papers. Subjects relate to Kendall's political and business affairs and his activities as Indian agent. Correspondents include: Asahel Bush, Hubert Howe Bancroft, David Logan, L. F. Grover, J. N. King, O. B. McFadden, J. L. Parrish, W. N. Rector, and E. H. Wilson. Of particular interest is a file of applications for positions in the Indian agency, 1861-1862, and applications to trade with the Nez Percé Indians, 1861. Among the personal letters is one from James Ripley Osgood, 1859 November 30, describing cultural and political conditions in Boston.
The collection is arranged in one series.
The collection is open to the public.
Letter of James Ripley Osgood was a gift of H. B. McElroy, 1916 April.
Scrapbook 112, page 27, Oregon Historical Society Research Library.
Information on the Kendall-Howe feud can be found in the file "Kendall, B. F.," in the Biography File, Oregon Historical Society Research Library.
The collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings:
Kendall, B. F. (Benjamin Freeman), 1829-1863--Correspondence.; Osgood, James R. (James Ripley), 1836-1892--Correspondence.
Overland Press (Olympia, Wash.)
Olympia (Wash.)--History.; Washington (State)--History--To 1889.
Indian agents--Washington (State).; Journalists--Washington (State)--History.; Nez Perceé Indians.
Journalism; Native Americans; Olympia; Washington (State)
Letters (correspondence).
Journalist.
- Letters to Kendall, political and business, 1857-1862, 1916 (Folder 1)
  M. Bachelder, Nov. 17, 1861, Dec. 16, 18, 1862, three
  H. H. Bancroft, Mar. 8, 1860
  Wm. H. Barnhart, May 5, 1862
  H. H, Black, Aug. 6, 1862
  M. Chappelin, Oct. 28, 1862
  E. S. Fowler, Dec. 11, 1862
  L. F. Grover, Mar. 16, 1862
  Dexter A. Hawkins, June 26, 1860, May 12, 1862, two
  G. Hays, Apr. 19, Sept. 21, 1862, two
  James M. Hays, Oct. 10, 1861
  Anson Henry, May 22, 1862
  Edward Huggins, Dec. 11, 1862
  L. D. Howe, Oct. 16, 1861
  R. G. Kendall, Mar. 13, 1859
  S. G. Kendall, Aug. 29, 1861-Oct. 30, 1862, three
  B. W. Kimball, Aug. 28-Sept. 26, 1862, three
  J. Nevin King, Sept. 7, 1861
  Edward Lander, Jan. 15, 1858
  T. F. Marks, Oct. 14, 1861
  O. B. McFadden, Aug. 7, 1862
  J. H. McKee, Jan. 25, 1862
  W. Medill, June 17, 1857
  W. E. Miles, May 12. 1859 (?)
  James R. Osgood, Nov. 30, 1859
  Geo. Parkinson, Aug. 9, 1862
  J. L. Parrish. & Co., Aug. 1, 1862
  Childs Peterson, June 13, 1860
  H. Race, Dec. 18, 1862
  Roberts, George B., Oct. 3, Nov 18, 1862, 2 letters
  L. H. Roberts, Feb. 21, 1860
  John H. Scranton, May 22, 1862
  Thos. H. Smith, Feb. 13, 1860
  H. Q. Tibbets, Dec. 20, 1862
  Wm. Utter, Apr. 17, 1860
  E. A. Willson, Oct. 1, 1862
  E. H. Wilson, Sept. 2, 1862
  C. H. Woodard, June 12, 1862
- Letters to Kendall, legal and business, 1855-1862 (Folder 2)
  C. H. Armstrong, Apr. 27, 1862
  Albert G. Balch, July 26, 1862
  Dan'l F. Bradford, July 11, 1859
  H. H. Byrne, Jan. 31, Mar. 22, 1860, two
  L. H. Calkins, July 25, 1858
  James Cawley, Nov. 17, 1862
  J. S. Clendenin, Mar. 10, 1805, plus three enclosures
  John Collins, Aug. 8, 1862
  B. F. Dennison, Dec. 10, 1862
  D. W. Douthitt, Aug. 30, 1862
  John Evans, June 29, 1857
  Fitzhugh, Apr. 18, 1860
  George Gallagher, Aug. 20, 1862
  Julie Gilmore, Mar. 25, 1860; Dec. 16, 1862, two
  E. Greenbaum, July 10, 1860
  John R. Jackson, Mar. 14, Apr. 11, 1860, two
  Isaac S. Josephi, Nov. 28, 1862
  David Logan, Aug. 25, 1862
  Wm. H. Molthrop, Mar. 9, 1860
  Robert Mows, Mar. 2, 1859
  E. E. Rogers, Aug. 11, 1862
  Charles C. Terry, June 18, 1862
  Thomas Wallace, Nov, 2, 1859-Apr. 23, 1860, six
  C. H. West, Feb. 23, 1858
  Elisha Whittlesey, Nov. 18, 1856, Feb. 23, 1857, two plus enclosure
  John A. Wills, Feb. 2, 1860, Oct. 6, 1862
- Letters to Kendall, Indian affairs, 1862 (Folder 3)
  Henri M. Chase, May 25, 1862
  H. H. Mc Near, May 20, 1862
  Wm. H. Rector, Feb. 15, 1862
  Amos Reed, March 7, 1862
  R. R. Thompson, Feb. 18, 1862
- Applications for jobs on Indian reservations, 1861-1862 (Folder 4)
- Applications to trade with Nez Percé Indians, 1861 (Folder 5)
- Bounty land claims statements, 1856-1858 (Folder 6)
- Legal documents and papers, 1855-1860 (Folder 7)
- Legal documents and papers, circa 1855-1870 (Folder 8)
- Depositions by employees of Indian agency, 1862 (Folder 9)
- General materials, 1853-1870 (Folder 10)
- Overland Press materials, 1862 (Folder 11)
- Receipts and accounts, circa 1856-1861 (Folder 12)